Guide to the University of Utah - Departments of Modern Dance and Ballet Theses collection: 1967-2001 1967-2001
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
University of Utah - Departments of Modern Dance and Ballet Theses collection: 1967-2001
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0322
University of Utah - Departments of Modern Dance and Ballet (U.S.)
2 DVDs, 12 VHS videocassettes, 11 U-matic videocassettes, 2 2-inch videotapes, 43 1-inch videotapes, 40 1/2-inch videotapes, 1 16mm film, 5 8mm films, 1 Super8mm film
The University of Utah Dance Theses Collection in the Audio Visual Archives consists of 124 recordings, ranging from 1967 to 2001, of graduate thesis concerts presented by MFA candidates from the Departments of Ballet and of Modern Dance. These departments are now separate, but were formerly a single combined department. The portion of this collection that is presented online consists of digitized VHS and U-Matic tapes. The quality of the digitized version of these tapes has been greatly affected by deterioration, demonstrating the need for greater preservation and digitization of audio-visual materials.
Historical Note
The University of Utah’s dance program has two departments within the College of Fine Arts: the Department of Modern Dance and the Department of Ballet. The heritage of dance at the University of Utah began in 1892 with a program developed by Maud May Babcock, the first female member of the University’s faculty. Babcock founded the University of Utah Departments of Speech and of Physical Education, the original departments to have housed dance majors before they were formally combined into a single department under the College of Fine Arts in 1966. Prior to the integration, the Department of Modern Dance was part of the Department of Physical Education and Ballet was part of the Department of Theatre.
The earliest record of dance courses at the University of Utah occurred in 1906 when dance was offered as a general physical education course. Dance wasn’t established as a major until 1953, when Elizabeth R. Hayes, appointed Director of Modern Dance in 1940, instituted it as a part of the Physical Education Department.
A ballet emphasis was not created until 1951 when William F. Christensen was offered the position of professor of ballet. His career at the University of Utah began in 1949 when President A. Ray Olpin invited him to choreograph the University of Utah’s Summer Festival Productions, a series of musicals and operas performed outside in the University’s stadium. After two years choreographing this program, he was offered the position which created one of the first ballet programs at an American university. Under his leadership, ballet became a “Field of Emphasis” with a departmental major in Speech in 1953 (Habel, 2010, p. 26). In 1962, a BFA degree with a major in Ballet was offered through the College of Fine Arts.
In 1966, the new Ballet and Modern Dance Department was formed with D. Gordan Paxman as Departmental Chairman, Willam F. Christensen as Director of Ballet, and Elizabeth R. Hayes as Director of Modern Dance. The combined department eventually separated in 1977 due to an inability, according to Hayes, to find anyone to chair the combined departments who could satisfy both the ballet and modern dance faculties. The two departments, although separate, are still housed in the College of Fine Arts.
In 1988, Hayes officially retired from the department in June after 48 years, having taught longer than any other woman faculty member at the University of Utah.
HISTORY OF THE NEW AND OLD DANCE BUILDINGS
The Departments of Modern Dance and Ballet are currently housed in the Alice Sheets Marriott Center for Dance, named after the wife of J. Willard Marriott, businessman and entrepreneur for whom the university’s library had been named.
Funding for the much-needed new building was an arduous task, taking over two decades to finally fund. Formally, dance was housed in the old Physical Education complex directly west of the Park Building. The building, constructed around 1905, eventually came to be known as the “Dance Building.” Originally built for physical education, it had been used for varying purposes through the years, including as a student health facility, a university cafeteria, biology and pharmacy laboratories, and as computer science classrooms and offices.
By the mid-eighties, the building was neither safe nor functional. It did not meet building and safety codes, nor did it meet the needs of the growing Departments of Ballet and Modern Dance. Several proposals for a new dance building were submitted to the State Legislature, but they remained a low priority on the building list for twenty-five years until the State Fire Marshall condemned the structure in 1984.
At this point, the Utah State Legislature appropriated $3.04 million for a new dance building, and in 1986, the J. Willard Marriott family contributed the remaining $2 million needed to fund the new dance building.
DESIGN AND CONSTRUCTION
M. Ray Kingston and Kip Harris, partners in FFKR Architects/Planners and Interior Design, collaborated on the design for the new facility. Having already designed the Salt Lake City Symphony Hall and the Randall L. Jones Theater for the Shakespearean festival in Cedar City, the firm offered the experience in designing spaces for the Arts. Kingston, lead architect on the project, had studied modern dance at the university in the 1950s while working towards his architectural degree. He was adamant that the building’s design meet the classroom and performance needs of the dance departments and their students. The building was specifically designed with the “comfort, convenience and aesthetic needs of the dancers in mind” (Habel, 2010, p. 400).
The building was constructed of red brick and Utah sandstone, and although architecturally contemporary, it blended with historic campus structures. At the heart of the three-story building are six large dance studios, a 333-seat professional theatre, classrooms on each floor, a faculty preparation studio on the third floor, locker rooms with stage access, a box office, administrative and faculty offices on the second floor, and an outdoor sky deck on the third level.
The formal performance space in the Marriott Center for Dance was named in honor of Elizabeth R. Hayes and Willam F. Christensen, in recognition of their outstanding contributions to dance and the University of Utah.
The 1988–1989 academic year was the last year that classes and performances were held in the old Dance Building. On September 25, 1989, the new 64,400 square-foot Alice Sheets Marriott Center for Dance building opened its doors to students, and ushered in a new era in the department’s history.
NOTABLE ALUMNI
Faculty and graduates of the University of Utah’s Ballet Department were fundamental in the formation and growth of Ballet West, Utah’s major professional ballet company. In 1955, Christensen and the University Theatre Ballet presented the first production of the Nutcracker in the University of Utah's Kingsbury Hall, a production that has become an annual Christmas treat for Salt Lake City audiences.
In the 1960s, two different professional modern dance companies were established by alumni. The Ririe-Woodbury Dance Company was formed in 1964 by Shirley Ririe and Joan Woodbury, professors of modern dance at the University. In 1966, the Repertory Dance Theatre was opened which has such dancers as Merce Cunnigham and Doris Humphrey among their professionals.
In 1966, a $370,000 grant was made to the University of Utah by the Rockefeller Foundation to establish the Utah Repertory Dance Theatre (RDT), the first full time modern dance company outside of New York City. The grant was the first of its kind awarded to a university by the foundation. The project director was Virginia Tanner, a Salt Lake native, nationally recognized children’s dance educator, and founder of the Utah Children’s Dance Theatre (1949).
Both RDT and Ririe-Woodbury received local and national recognition for their work, participating in educational and community outreach programs throughout the country. Both companies had a symbiotic relationship with the modern dance program at the University of Utah. While the companies offered professional performing opportunities for skilled dance students, the department provided a pool of students from which the companies drew members. Through the years many modern dance students performed professionally with RDT and Ririe-Woodbury.
Several alumni of the Departments of Ballet and Modern Dance became notable dancers and faculty members of the University of Utah’s dance departments.
Bené Arnold
Arnold received both her B.F.A. and M.F.A. from the University of Utah’s Department of Ballet. From 1963 to 1975, she served as the ballet mistress for the future company, Ballet West. In 1975, she joined the University of Utah Department of Ballet faculty. In 1998, Arnold became the first woman and only faculty member from Fine Arts and Humanities to be named Distinguished Professor. When Arnold retired from the University of Utah, she was named Distinguished Professor Emerita. Since 2008, Arnold has served as the Interim Chair of the Department of Ballet.
Phyllis Haskell
In August of 1987, Phyllis Haskell joined the department as the Chair of the Department of Modern Dance. Haskell was a 1971 MFA graduate of the University of Utah. She was also a member of the Ririe-Woodbury Dance Company from 1971 to 1979, and acted as the company’s Assistant Artistic Director from 1977 to 1979.
Tomm Ruud
After 10 years with William Christensen's Ballet West in Salt Lake City, Tomm Ruud joined the San Francisco Ballet in 1975. Ruud was best known for his role as Drosselmeyer in the Nutcracker.
Donna White
In 1979, Donna White joined the faculty as an Associate Instructor having finished her MFA the previous year. White came to the faculty with a strong performance and choreography background. She danced with Ririe-Woodbury (1971-76); performed and taught with Tandy Beal and Company (1977-87); and founded Donna White and DANCEWORKS in 1979, a company for which she directed, choreographed, and performed with until 1984.
Donna is currently Professor in the Department of Modern Dance at the University of Utah and was the former Chair of the Department from 2002-2010. Donna has been on the Modern Dance faculty since 1996. She also holds the position of Associate Dean of the Graduate School at the University.
Reference List
Habel, S. (2010). History of the Modern Dance Program at the University of Utah. Unpublished master’s thesis, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah.
This collection holds the master's theses of many students who became notable dancers, and faculty members of the University of Utah’s dance departments.
22 items in the collection are viewable online.
The theses in the collection that are on actual film should be in fairly good condition; the quality of the tapes, however, has deteriorated leading to poor video quality. Please note that viewing options for 1/2", 1", 2", and U-matic formats are nearly obsolete. If you are interested in a digital transfer of a format that may have gone into obsolesence, please contact Multimedia Archives at 801-585-3073 for more information.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
For a full list of dance theses held by the Audio Visual Archives, please visit our Dance Subject Guide.
Department of Ballet and Modern Dance--Utah-History; Department of Modern Dance--Utah-History; Department of Ballet--Utah-History; Fine Arts; Performing Arts; Salt Lake City; Utah; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Moving images; Sound recordings
- Fractured Figments by Suzanne Grace, April 1978; U-matic videocassette Combination of color and black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 1)
  Full description and digitized video here
- Phases I and Phases II by Linda H. Hoffmaster, undated; 1 U-matic videocassette, 2 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 60 mins (Cassette 2)
- 'Til the Cows Come Home by Sybil Dianne Huskey, 1979; U-matic videocassette Color, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 3)
- A Blue Feathered Star Shimmer Moon Rhyme Magic Show by Lorrie Sue Keller, 1981; U-matic videocassette Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 4)
- Space Games by Linda Banks LeBarron, 1978; U-matic videocassette Black and white, Sound, 8 mins (Cassette 5)
- Radish Games by Sally Ann Lewiecki, 09 February and 10 February 1978; U-matic videocassette Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 6)
- An Analysis of the Creative Process of Two Choreographic Works by Mary Lynne Shupe, 1973; U-matic videocassette Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 7)
- Danceworks by Donna M. White, 1979; U-matic videocassette Black and white, Sound, 60 mins. total (8 copies) (Cassette 8)
- In the Process by Walter White, Jr., 1978; U-matic videocassette, 2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 60 mins (Cassette 9)
- Crossing Lines by Sara R. Wilbourne, 1978; U-matic videocassette, 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 23 mins (Cassette 10)
- What's the Point of Living if You Can't Horse Around a Little? by Mary Angela Wohl, 1978; U-matic videocassette Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 11)
- The Spirit by Katherine Abbott-Lewis, 1974; VHS videocassette, 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 12)
- Ariadne's Dance by Nancy Brooks, 14 May 1975; 2 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 13)
- Challenges in Performance and Choreography by Kathy Caton, August 1984; VHS videocassette, 1/2-inch videotape Color, Sound, 12 mins (Cassette 14)
- The Cognition of My Growth in Performance Attitude by Erh-Mei Chao, 1997; VHS videocassette Color, Sound, 40 mins (Cassette 15)
- Job by Robert Christianson, August 1976; 2 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 16)
- Connections by Nancy Lynne Dickson, 1977; 2 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 22 mins (Reel 17)
- The Power by Daphne M. Finnegan, 1977; 2 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 19 mins (Reel 18)
- Four Dance Pieces by Kristine Jean Halverson, 1981; VHS videocassette Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Cassette 19)
- Modern Dance as a Liturgical Art Form by Catherine Herbut, 1977; 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 20)
- Journey by Caroline Kittell Hunt, 2001; 2 VHS videocassette, 1 DVD Color, sound, 10 mins (Cassette 21)
- Facets of Turkish Culture Translated Through Dance by Maranee Claire Jones, May 1968; 8mm film (Reel 22)
- A Dance Theater Production for Children by Judith Mandeville, 1970; Super 8mm film (Reel 23)
- Secret Leaking by Beth A. Miklavcic and Douglas Miklos, 29, 30 January 1988; VHS videocassette (Cassette 24)
  Second Nature-Miklos
  Prelude to Tragedy-Miklos
  Woman Who Lives in a Shoe-Pak
  Distance Happens in No Time-Miklavcic
  Tally Ho-Miklavcic
  Photographic Memory-Miklavcic
  Blankets of Dreams-Miklos
  Chair Pillow
- Untitled by Linda Mitchell, May 1967; 2 8mm film (Reel 25)
- Catalli Carmina by Eric Brandt Nielsen, May 1973; 1 1-inch videotape, 1 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 26)
- 5 Dances Based on the Graphics of Kaethe Kollwitz by Andrea Olsen, 1972; 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 27)
- Gatherings by Cheryl Palonis, June 1976; 2 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 28)
- The Fault is the Earth's by Kathryn Marie, 1975; 2 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 29)
- Techniques and Styles of Jazz Dancing, 1967; 2 8mm film (Reel 30)
- Responsibilty to Form by Gregory Bryant Simione, 1983; VHS videocassette, 1/2-inch videotape Color, Sound, 50 mins (Cassette 31)
- Desert Canticle and On a Whim by Deborah Ann Stone, 1981; 2 VHS videocassette (Cassette 32)
- The Ancestors by Margaret Tcheng, 1975; 3 1-inch videotape (Reel 33)
- Discourse with the Earth by Jeanne Lynne Travers, August 1984; VHS videocassette (Cassette 34)
- Reflections in Three Dances by Sherrie Waggener, 1976; 2 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 35)
- Two Dance Pieces: Conformity vs. Individual Will and Dancers' Self-Accompaniment by Patricia L. Weeks, 1977; 2 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, sound, 20 mins (Reel 36)
- Come Watch Our Dance Class by Joan M. Dukes, 28 February 1969; 1-inch videotape (Reel 37)
  Use of a second grade curriculum as the point of origin for developing dance classes.
- When Summoned by J.W. Evans, 14 July 1970; 1-inch videotape (Reel 38)
- The Creation of Sunrise by Toni Tygesen Klein, June 1970; 1-inch videotape, 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 39)
- The Performance of Two Classical Ballet Roles, the Creation and Performance of an Original Abstract Ballet, and a Discussion of the Preparation of Each by Tomm C. Ruud, June 1970; 1-inch videotape (Reel 40)
  La Bagadere-classical ballet, male lead performed by Ruud
  Mobile-an abstract ballet, choreographed by Ruud, male lead performed by Ruud
- Investigation of Tension Release Methods for Performers by Kay Frances Silvey, undated; 1-inch videotape (Reel 41)
  Investigation of tensions of the body, the voice, and the interaction of the body and voice
- Portraits by James S. Coleman, 1988; 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Reel 42)
- The Maids by LeeAnn Hartley, 1977; 1/2-inch videotape, DVD 26 mins (Reel 43)
- Whispers of Wind in the Willows by Kathleen L. Hill, 1977; 2 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Reel 44)
- Performance with Performing Danscompany: An Analysis of 8 Roles, 1982; 1/2-inch videotape, 1 VHS videocassette Black and white, Sound, 115 mins (Reel 45)
- On the Freeway by Susan Jamieson, March 1977; 2 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 46)
- Spatial Envelopes-A Dance by Caroline W. Kittell, 1975; 2-inch videotape (Reel 47)
- Three Dances by Allan Michael David Lazar, undated; 2 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 30 mins (Reel 48)
- Joshua Giraffe by Dean Nelson, undated; 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 49)
- Windswept Place by JoAnna Mendl Shaw, 09/10 March 1976; 2 1/2-inch videotape (Reel 50)
- The Integration of Folk Dance into the Classical Ballet Technique by Wendy Jeanne Vaughn, June 1977; 2 1/2-inch videotape Black and white, Sound, 45 mins (Reel 51)
- Exploring Dance and Its Elements by Sharon Evans, 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 52)
- Untitled, undated; 1-inch videotape 60 mins (Reel 53)
  1. Lecture-Demonstartion(Haskell/McConnell)
  2. Zodiac
  3. Abyss
  4. 5 Dances from Gloriana
  5. Insect Trio: Bet, Jene, Dennis
- Pantomime, undated; 16mm film (Reel 54)
- Choreographers' Concert 1970, 1-inch videotape (Reel 55)
  1. Dismer-Jazz
  2. McConnell(Sichel)
  3. McEntee-Group
  4. Blank
  5. Wilson-Collage
  6. Sanderson-Authorized Personnel Only
- Choreographers' Concert 1972-Section 1, 1-inch videotape (Reel 56)
- Lifeline by John Wilson, 1972; 1-inch videotape (Reel 57)
  From Choreographer's Concert 1972-Section II
- Choreographers' Concert 1972-Section III, 1-inch videotape (Reel 58)
- Orchesis Choreoographers' Concert, 1969; 1-inch videotape (Reel 59)
- Orchesis Choreoographers' Concert, 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 60)
  1. Claudia Cannon
  2. Deborah Dunn
  3. Cathy Herbut
- Orchesis Choreographers' Concert, 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 61)
  1. Kadesch
  2. Andrea Olsen-Portraiture
- Spring Ballet Demonstration, 1969; 1-inch videotape (Reel 62)
- Mime Class, 1970; 1-inch videotape 8 mins (Reel 63)
  Abstract: a study of shapes, textures, and properties working together
  RubberBand
  Butterfly: slow-motion
  Conductor and Opera Singer: one person doing two characters
  Walk Study: fat person, prissy, tall and thin, sexy, Ardean Watts, drummer, shy boy
  Siblings
  Funeral
- An Evening of Renaissance and Baroque Dance by Roberta Jo Baumann, 1973; 1-inch videotape (Reel 64)
- In Transit by Viola Farber and Travelin by John Wilson, 1970; 1-inch videotape (Reel 65)
- Mirror and Sonata, undated; 1-inch videotape (Reel 66)
- Pas de Quatre and Sylphides Variation by Victor Reed, undated; 1-inch videotape (Reel 67)
- Fall Gently by Cliff Kenter and Incantation by Joanne Woobury, 1972; 1-inch videotape (Reel 68)
- Choreographers' Concert-Part II, 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 69)
  1. Metamorphic Musings by John Wilson
  2. 3 Promenades to the Lord by John Butler
  3. Now by Shirley Ririe
- Finally Together, 1973; 1-inch videotape (Reel 70)
  Ballet and Modern Dance Combined Production
- Gioacometti-Sculpture Garden by Jennifer Muller and Human Image by John Wilson, 1973; 1-inch videotape (Reel 71)
- Fields of Passing by Anthony LaGiglia, 1974; 1-inch videotape (Reel 72)
- Untitled, undated; 1-inch videotape (Reel 73)
- Dance 1970, 1-inch videotape (Reel 74)
  Earth-Sea-Fire-Air by John Wilson
  Some Song by Shirley Ririe
  Incantation by Joan Woodbury
- Dance 1973, 1-inch videotape (Reel 75)
  Jennifer Muller
  John Wilson
  Shirley Ririe
- Dance 1973, 1-inch videotape (Reel 76)
- Italian Symphony by Kenneth Mitchell, 1968; 1-inch videotape (Reel 77)
- Dance 1973, 1-inch videotape (Reel 78)
  Loabelle Mangelson
  Louis Bach-Murran
- Orpheo and Euridice by Vicki Ramey, 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 79)
  Act I
- Orpheo and Euridice by Vicki Ramey, 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 80)
  Act II
- Cycles by Bene Arnold, undated; 1-inch videotape (Reel 81)
- A Dance Drama by Carolyn Rosenfield, 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 82)
- Untitled by Phyllis Haskell and Patti McConnell, 1971; 1-inch videotape 56 mins (Reel 83)
  1. Lecture-Demonstration
- Dances Inspired by Navaho by Nancy Isabel Lee, June 1971; 1-inch videotape (Reel 84)
- The Development of a Performer by Christopher Fair, 1972; 1-inch videotape (Reel 85)
- Unidentified, undated; 1-inch videotape (Reel 86)